This lecture is about
the expectation-maximization
algorithm,
also called the EM algorithm.
In this lecture, we're
going to continue
the discussion of
probabilistic topic models.
In particular, we're going to
introduce the EM algorithm,
which is a family of
useful algorithms for computing
the maximum likelihood estimate
of mixture models.
So this is now
familiar scenario of
using a two component,
the mixture model, to try
to factor out
the background words
from one topic word
of distribution here.
So we're interested in
computing this estimate,
and we're going to try to adjust
these probability values to
maximize the probability
of the observed document.
Note that we assume that all
the other parameters are known.
So the only thing unknown is
the word probabilities
given by theta sub.
In this lecture, we're
going to look into how to
compute this maximum
likelihood estimate.
Now, let's start with the idea of
separating the words in
the text data into two groups.
One group would be explained
by the background model.
The other group would
be explained by
the unknown topic
word distribution.
After all, this is
the basic idea of mixture model.
But suppose we actually
know which word is from
which distribution?
So that would mean, for example,
these words the, is,
and we are known to
be from this background
word distribution.
On the other hand, the
other words text, mining,
clustering etc are known to be
from the topic word distribution.
If you can see the color,
then these are shown in blue.
These blue words are then
assumed that to be from
the topic word distribution.
If we already know how
to separate these words,
then the problem of estimating
the word distribution
would be extremely simple.
If you think about
this for a moment,
you'll realize that, well,
we can simply take
all these words that are known
to be from this word
distribution theta sub d
and normalize them.
So indeed this problem would be
very easy to solve if we had
known which words are from
which a distribution precisely,
and this is in fact
making this model no
longer a mixture model
because we can already observe
which distribution has been
used to generate
which part of the data.
So we actually go back to
the single word
distribution problem.
In this case let's call
these words that are
known to be from theta d,
a pseudo document of d prime,
and now all we need to
do is just normalize
these words counts
for each word w_i.
That's fairly straightforward.
It's just dictated by the
maximum likelihood estimator.
Now, this idea however
doesn't work because
we in practice don't really
know which word is from
which distribution,
but this gives us
the idea of perhaps we
can guess which word is
from which it is written.
Specifically given
all the parameters,
can we infer the distribution
a word is from.
So let's assume that we actually
know tentative probabilities for
these words in theta sub d.
So now all the parameters
are known for this mixture model,
and now let's consider
a word like a "text".
So the question is, do you
think "text" is more likely
having been generated from
theta sub d or from
theta sub of b?
So in other words,
we want to infer
which distribution has been
used to generate this text.
Now, this inference process is
a typical Bayesian inference
situation where we have
some prior about
these two distributions.
So can you see what
is our prior here?
Well, the prior here is
the probability of
each distribution.
So the prior is given by
these two probabilities.
In this case, the prior
is saying that each model
is equally likely,
but we can imagine perhaps a
different prior is possible.
So this is called a prior
because this is our guess of
which distribution has
been used to generate
a word before we even
off reserve the word.
So that's why we
call it the prior.
So if we don't observe the word,
we don't know what word
has been observed.
Our best guess is to say
well, they're equally likely.
All right. So it's
just flipping a coin.
Now in Bayesian inference we
typically learn with update
our belief after we have
observed the evidence.
So what is the evidence here?
Well, the evidence
here is the word text.
Now that we know we're
interested in the word text.
So text that can be
regarded as evidence,
and if we use
Bayes rule to combine the
prior and the data likelihood,
what we will end up
with is to combine the
prior with the likelihood
that you see here,
which is basically
the probability of
the word text from
each distribution.
We see that in both cases
the text is possible.
Note that even in the background
it is still possible,
it just has a very
small probability.
So intuitively what would
be your guess in this case.
Now if you're like many others,
you are guess text
is probably from
theta sub d. It's more likely
from theta sub d. Why?
You will probably see that
it's because text that has
a much higher probability
here by the theta sub d,
then by the background model
which has a very
small probability.
By this we're going to say, well,
text is more likely from
theta sub d. So you see
our guess of which
distribution has been
used to generate
the text would depend on
how high the probability of
the text is in
each word distribution.
We can do, tend to guess
the distribution that gives us
a word a higher probability,
and this is likely to
maximize the likelihood.
So we're going to choose
a word that has
a higher likelihood.
So in other words,
we're going to compare
these two probabilities of
the word given by
each distributions.
But our guess must also
be affected by the prior.
So we also need to
compare these two priors.
Why? Because imagine if we
adjust these probabilities,
we're going to say
the probability of choosing
a background model is
almost 100 percent.
Now, if you have that kind
of strong prior,
then that would
affect your guess.
You might think,
well, wait a moment,
maybe text could have been
from the background as well.
Although the probability
is very small here,
the prior is very high.
So in the end, we have
to combine the two,
and the base formula provides us
a solid and principled way
of making this kind of
guess to quantify that.
So more specifically,
let's think about
the probability that
this word has been generated in
fact from from theta sub d. Well,
in order for texts
to be generated from
theta sub d two things
must happen.
First, the theta sub d
must have been selected,
so we have the selection
probability here.
Secondly, we also have to
actually have observed text
from the distribution.
So when we multiply
the two together,
we get the probability
that text has in
fact been generated from
theta sub d. Similarly,
for the background model,
the probability of generating
text is another product
of a similar form.
Now, we also introduced
the latent variable
z here to denote
whether the word is from
the background or the topic.
When z is zero,
it means it's from the topic
theta sub d. When it's one,
it means it's from
the background theta sub b.
So now we have
the probability that text
is generated from each.
Then we can simply normalize
them to have an estimate
of the probability
that the word text is
from theta sub d or
from theta sub b.
Then equivalently, the
probability that z is equal to
zero given that
the observed evidence is text.
So this is application
of Bayes rule.
But this step is very
crucial for understanding
the EM algorithm because
if we can do this,
then we would be able to first
initialize the parameter values
somewhat randomly,
and then we're going to take
a guess of these z values.
Which distributing has been
used to generate which word,
and the initialized
the parameter values would
allow us to have a complete
specification of
the mixture model
which further allows us to
apply Bayes rule to infer
which distribution is more
likely to generate each word.
This prediction
essentially helped us
to separate the words from
the two distributions.
Although we can't
separate them for sure,
but we can separate them
probabilistically as shown here.