This lecture is about
the mixture model estimation.
In this lecture, we're
going to continue
discussing probabilistic
topic models.
In particular, we're going
to talk about the how to
estimate the parameters
of a mixture model.
So let's first look
at our motivation
for using a mixture model,
and we hope to effect out
the background words from
the topic word distribution.
So the idea is to assume that
the text data actually
contain two kinds of words.
One kind is from
the background here,
so the "is", "we" etc.
The other kind is from
our topic word distribution
that we're interested in.
So in order to solve
this problem of
factoring out background words,
we can set up our mixture
model as follows.
We are going to assume that
we already know the parameters
of all the values for
all the parameters in
the mixture model except for
the word distribution of
Theta sub d which is our target.
So this is a case of
customizing probably
some model so that we
embedded the unknown variables
that we are interested in,
but we're going to
simplify other things.
We're going to assume
we have knowledge about
others and this is
a powerful way of
customizing a model
for a particular need.
Now you can imagine, we
could have assumed that
we also don't know the
background word distribution,
but in this case,
our goal is to affect out
precisely those high probability
in the background words.
So we assume the background
model is already fixed.
The problem here is,
how can we adjust the Theta sub
d in order to maximize
the probability of
the observed document
here and we assume all the
other parameters are known?
Now, although we
designed the modal
heuristically to try to
factor out these
background words,
it's unclear whether if
we use maximum
likelihood estimator,
we will actually end up having
a word distribution where
the common words like "the" will
be indeed having smaller
probabilities than before.
So now, in this case,
it turns out that
the answer is yes.
When we set up the probabilistic
modeling this way,
when we use maximum
likelihood estimator,
we will end up having
a word distribution where
the common words
would be factored
out by the use of
the background distribution.
So to understand why this is so,
it's useful to examine
the behavior of a mixture model.
So we're going to look
at a very simple case.
In order to understand
some interesting behaviors
of a mixture model,
the observed patterns
here actually are
generalizable to mixture
model in general,
but it's much easier to
understand this behavior when
we use a very simple case
like what we're seeing here.
So specifically in this case,
let's assume that
the probability of
choosing each of the two models
is exactly the same.
So we're going to flip
a fair coin to decide
which model to use.
Furthermore, we are going
to assume there are
precisely to words,
"the" and "text."
Obviously, this is
a very naive oversimplification
of the actual text,
but again, it is useful
to examine the behavior
in such a special case.
So we further assume that,
the background model gives
probability of 0.9 to
the word "the" and "text" 0.1.
Now, let's also assume that
our data is extremely simple.
The document has just two words
"text" and then "the."
So now, let's write down
the likelihood function
in such a case.
First, what's the probability
of "text" and what's the
probability of "the"?
I hope by this point,
you will be able
to write it down.
So the probability of "text" is
basically a sum of
two cases where each case
corresponds to each of
the water distribution and
it accounts for the two ways
of generating text.
Inside each case, we have
the probability of choosing
the model which is
0.5 multiplied by the probability
of observing "text"
from that model.
Similarly, "the" would
have a probability of
the same form just as it
was different exactly
probabilities.
So naturally,
our likelihood function
is just the product of the two.
So it's very easy to see that,
once you understand
what's the probability of
each word and which
is also why it's so
important to understand what's
exactly the probability of
observing each word from
such a mixture model.
Now, the interesting
question now is,
how can we then optimize
this likelihood?
Well, you will notice that,
there are only two variables.
They are precisely
the two probabilities
of the two words
"text" and "the" given
by Theta sub d. This is
because we have assumed that,
all the other
parameters are known.
So now, the question is
a very simple algebra question.
So we have a simple expression
with two variables and we hope
to choose the values of
these two variables to
maximize this function.
It's exercises that we have
seen some simple
algebra problems,
and note that the two
probabilities must sum to one.
So there's some constraint.
If there were
no constraint of course,
we will set both probabilities to
their maximum value which
would be one to maximize this,
but we can't do that
because "text" and
"the" must sum to one.
We can't give those a
probability of one.
So now the question is,
how should we allocate
the probability in
the mass between the two words?
What do you think?
Now, it will be useful to look at
this formula for
moment and to see
intuitively what
we do in order to
set these probabilities to
maximize the value
of this function.
If we look into this further,
then we'll see
some interesting behavior
of the two component
models in that,
they will be
collaborating to maximize
the probability of
the observed data which
is dictated by the maximum
likelihood estimator,
but they're also
competing in some way.
In particular, they
would be competing on
the words and they
will tend to bet
high probabilities on
different words to avoid
this competition in some sense
or to gain advantage
in this competition.
So again, looking at this
objective function and we have
a constraint on
the two probabilities,
now if you look at
the formula intuitively,
you might feel that
you want to set
the probability of "text"
to be somewhat larger than "the".
This intuition can
be well-supported
by mathematical fact which is,
when the sum of
two variables is a
constant then the product of
them which is maximum
then they are equal,
and this is a fact that
we know from algebra.
Now, if we plug that in,
we will would mean
that we have to make
the two probabilities equal.
When we make them equal
and then if we consider
the constraint that we can
easily solve this problem,
and the solution is the
probability of "text"
would be 0.9 and probability
of "the" is 0.1.
As you can see indeed,
the probability of text
is not much larger than
probability of "the" and
this is not the case when we
have just one distribution.
This is clearly because of
the use of the
background model which
assign a very high probability
to "the" low
probability to "text".
If you look at the equation,
you will see obviously
some interaction of
the two distributions here.
In particular, you will see in
order to make them equal and then
the probability assigned
by Theta sub d must
be higher for a word that has
a smaller probability
given by the background.
This is obvious from
examining this equation
because "the" background part is
weak for "text" it's a small.
So in order to
compensate for that,
we must make the probability
of "text" that's given by
Theta sub d somewhat
larger so that the two sides
can be balanced.
So this is in fact
a very general behavior
of this mixture model.
That is, if one distribution
assigns a high probability
to one word than another,
then the other distribution
would tend to do the opposite.
Basically, it would discourage
other distributions to do the
same and this is to
balance them out so that,
we can account for all words.
This also means that,
by using a background
model that is
fixed to assign high probabilities
to background words,
we can indeed encourage
the unknown topic
word distribution to
assign smaller probabilities
for such common words.
Instead, put more probability
mass on the content words
that cannot be explained well by
the background
model meaning that,
they have a very
small probability
from the background
model like "text" here.