This lecture is about the
textual representation.
In this lecture, we are going
to discuss textual
representation,
and discuss how natural
language processing can
allow us to represent text
in many different ways.
Let's take a look at this
example sentence again.
We can represent this sentence
in many different ways.
First, we can always
represent such a sentence
as a string of characters.
This is true for
all the languages
when we store them
in the computer.
When we store a natural
language sentence
as a string of characters,
we have perhaps the most general
way of representing text
since we always use
this approach to
represent any text data.
But unfortunately, using
such a representation will not
help us to do semantic analysis,
which is often needed
for many applications
of text mining.
The reason is because we're
not even recognizing words.
So as a string,
we're going to keep
all the spaces
and these ASCII symbols.
We can perhaps count what's
the most frequent character
in English text,
or the correlation
between those characters,
but we can't really
analyze semantics.
Yet, this is the most
general way of representing
text because we can use
this to represent any
natural language text.
If we try to do
a little bit more natural
language processing
by doing word segmentation,
then we can obtain a
representation of the same text,
but in the form of a
sequence of words.
So here we see that
we can identify
words like a dog is chasing etc.
Now with this level
of representation,
we certainly can do
a lot of things,
and this is mainly because
words are the basic units
of human communication
in natural language,
so they are very powerful.
By identifying words, we can for
example easily count what are
the most frequent words in
this document or in
the whole collection etc.
These words can be used to form
topics when we combine
related words together,
and some words are positive,
some words negative, so we can
also do sentiment analysis.
So representing text data
as a sequence of words
opens up a lot of interesting
analysis possibilities.
However, this level of
representation is slightly
less general than string
of characters because in
some languages such as Chinese,
it's actually not
that easy to identify
all the word boundaries
because in such a language,
you see text as a sequence of
characters with
no space in between.
So you'll have to rely on
some special techniques
to identify words.
In such a language,
of course then,
we might make mistakes
in segmenting words.
So the sequence of
words representation is
not as robust as
string of characters.
But in English, it's very
easy to obtain this level
of representation,
so we can do that all the time.
Now, if we go further
to do naturally
language processing,
we can add a part of speech tags.
Now once we do that,
we can count, for example,
the most frequent
nouns or what kind of
nouns are associated with
what kind of verbs etc.
So this opens up
a little bit more
interesting opportunities
for further analysis.
Note that I use a plus sign
here because by
representing text as a sequence
of part of speech tags,
we don't necessarily replace
the original word
sequence written.
Instead, we add this as
an additional way of
representing text data,
so that now the data is
represented as both a sequence
of words and a sequence
of part of speech tags.
This enriches the
representation of text data,
and thus also enables
more interesting analysis.
If we go further, then we'll
be pausing the sentence
often to obtain
a syntactic structure.
Now this of course,
further open up
a more interesting analysis
of, for example,
the writing styles or
correcting grammar mistakes.
If we go further for
semantic analysis,
then we might be able to
recognize dog as an animal,
and we also can recognize
a boy as a person,
and playground as a location.
We can further analyze
their relations, for example,
dog is chasing the boy and
the boy is on the playground.
Now this will add
more entities and
relations through
entity relation recreation.
At this level,
then we can do even more
interesting things.
For example, now we
can count easily
the most frequent person that's
mentioning this whole collection
of news articles,
or whenever you
mention this person,
you also tend to see mentioning
of another person etc.
So this is a very
useful representation,
and it's also related to
the knowledge graph that
some of you may have heard
of that Google is doing as
a more semantic way of
representing text data.
However, it's also less robust
than sequence of words or
even syntactical analysis
because it's not
always easy to identify
all the entities with
the right types,
and we might make mistakes,
and relations are
even harder to find,
and we might make mistakes.
So this makes this level of
representation less robust,
yet it's very useful.
Now if we move further
to logical condition,
then we can have predicates
and even inference rules.
With inference rules, we can
infer interesting derived
facts from the text,
so that's very useful.
But unfortunately,
at this level of
representation is even less
robust and we can make
mistakes and we can't do
that all the time for
all kinds of sentences.
Finally, speech acts would
add a yet another level
of repetition of the intent
of saying this sentence.
So in this case,
it might be a request.
So knowing that would
allow us to analyze
even more interesting
things about
this observer or the author
of this sentence.
What's the intention
of saying that?
What's scenarios? What kind
of actions would be made?
So this is another level
of analysis that would
be very interesting.
So this picture shows
that if we move down,
we generally see
more sophisticated
natural language processing
techniques to be used.
Unfortunately,
such techniques would
require more human effort,
and they are less accurate.
That means there are mistakes.
So if we add an texts that are at
the levels that are
representing deeper
analysis of language,
then we have to
tolerate the errors.
So that also means it's
still necessary to combine
such deep analysis with
shallow analysis based on,
for example, sequence of words.
On the right side,
you'll see the arrow points
down to indicate that.
As we go down,
we are representation
of text is closer
to knowledge representation
in our mind,
and need for solving
a lot of problems.
Now this is desirable because as
we can represent text at
the level of knowledge,
we can easily extract
the knowledge.
That's the purpose
of text-mining.
So there is a trade-off
here between doing
a deeper analysis that
might have errors but would give
us direct knowledge that
can be extracted from text.
Doing shallow analysis, which
is more robust but
wouldn't actually
give us the necessary deeper
representation of knowledge.
I should also say that
text data are generated by
humans and are meant to
be consumed by humans.
So as a result, in
text data analysis,
text-mining humans play
a very important role,
they are always in the loop.
Meaning that we should optimize
the collaboration of
humans and computers.
So in that sense,
it's okay that computers
may not be able
to have compute accurately
representation of text data,
and the patterns
that are extracted
from text data can be
interpreted by humans,
and humans can
guide the computers
to do more accurate analysis
by annotating more data,
by providing features
to guide a machine
learning programs to make
them work more effectively.