In this lecture, we continue
discussing Paradigmatical
Relation Discovery.
Earlier we introduced
a method called
Expected Overlap of
Words in Context.
In this method, we
represent each context by
a word vector that represents
the probability of a
word in the context.
We measure the similarity
by using the.product,
which can be interpreted as
the probability that two
randomly picked words from
the two contexts are identical.
We also discussed
the two problems of this method.
The first is that
it favors matching
one frequent term very well over
matching more distinct terms.
It put too much emphasis on
matching one term very well.
The second is that it
treats every word equally.
Even a common word like
the will contribute
equally as content
word like eats.
So now we are
going to talk about how
to solve these problems.
More specifically, we're
going to introduce
some retrieval heuristics
used in text retrieval.
These heuristics can effectively
solve these problems,
as these problems also
occur in text retrieval
when we match a query that
though with a document vector.
So to address the first problem,
we can use a sublinear
transformation of tone frequency.
That is, we don't have to use
the raw frequency count of
a term to represent the context.
We can transform
it into some form
that wouldn't emphasize so
much on the raw frequency.
To address the
synchronous problem,
we can put more weight
on rare terms.
That is we can reward
matching a real-world.
This heuristic is called the IDF
term weighting in text retrieval.
IDF stands for
Inverse Document Frequency.
So now, we're going to talk about
the two heuristics
in more detail.
First let's talk about
the TF Transformation.
That is to convert
the raw count of
a word in the document
into some weight
that reflects our belief
about how important
this word in the document.
So that will be
denoted by TF of w,d.
That's shown in the y-axis.
Now, in general, there are
many ways to map that.
Let's first look at
the simple way of mapping.
In this case, we're
going to say, well,
any non-zero counts
will be mapped to
one and the zero count
will be mapped to zero.
So with this mapping
all the frequencies will be
mapped to only two
values; zero or one.
The mapping function is shown
here as a flat line here.
Now, this is naive
because it's not
the frequency of words.
However, this actually
has the advantage of
emphasizing matching all
the words in the context.
So it does not allow
a frequency of word to
dominate the matching.
Now, the approach
that we have taken
earlier in the expected
overlap count approach,
is a linear transformation.
We basically, take
y as the same as x.
So we use the raw count
as a representation.
That created the problem
that we just talked about namely;
it emphasize too much on just
matching one frequent term.
Matching one frequent term
can contribute a lot.
So we can have a lot
of other interesting
transformations
in between the two extremes,
and they generally form
a sublinear transformation.
So for example,
one possibility is to take
logarithm of the raw count,
and this will give us curve
that looks like this,
that you are seeing here.
In this case, you can see
the high frequency counts.
The high counts are
penalize a little bit,
so the curve is a sublinear
curve and it brings down
the weight of
those really high counts.
This is what we want,
because it prevents that
terms from dominating
the scoring function.
Now, there is also
another interesting
transformation called
a BM25 transformation which
has been shown to be very
effective for retrieval.
In this transformation, we have
a form that looks like this.
So it's k plus one multiplied
by x divided by x plus k,
where k is a parameter,
x is the count,
the raw count of a word.
Now, the transformation
is very interesting in
that it can actually go from
one extreme to the other
extreme by varying
k. It also interesting
that it has upper bound,
k plus one in this case.
So this puts
a very strict constraint
on high frequency terms,
because their weight would
never exceed k plus one.
As we vary k, if we can
simulate the two extremes.
So when k is set to zero,
we roughly have the 0,1 vector.
Whereas when we set k
to a very large value,
it will behave more like
the linear transformation.
So this transformation
function is by
far the most effective
transformation function for
text retrieval and it also makes
sense for our problem setup.
So we just talked about how
to solve the problem of
overemphasizing a frequency term
Now let's look at
the second problem,
and that is how we can
penalize popular terms.
Matching "the" is not surprising,
because "the" occurs everywhere.
But matching "eats"
would count a lot.
So how can we address
that problem?
Now in this case, we can
use the IDF weighting.
That's commonly
used in retrieval.
IDF stands for
Inverse Document Frequency.
Document frequency
means the count
of the total number of
documents that contain
a particular word.
So here we show that the IDF
measure is defined as
a logarithm function
of the number
of documents that match a
term or document frequency.
So K is the number of
documents containing word or
document frequency and M
here is the total number of
documents in the collection.
The IDF function is giving
a higher value for a lower K,
meaning that it
rewards rare term.
The maximum value is
log of M plus one.
That's when the word occurred
just once in a context.
So that's a very rare term,
the rare is term in
the whole collection.
The lowest value you can
see here is when K reaches
its maximum which would be M.
So that would be
a very low value,
close to zero in fact.
So this of course measure
is used in search where we
naturally have a collection.
In our case, what would
be our collection?
Well, we can also
use the context that
we can collect all the words
as our collection.
That is to say,
a word that's popular in
the collection in general,
would also have a low IDF.
Because depending on the dataset,
we can construct the context
vectors in different ways.
But in the end if a term is
very frequent in
the original dataset,
then it will still be frequent
in the collective
context documents.
So how can we add
these heuristics to
improve our similarity function?
Well, here's one way
and there are
many other ways
that are possible.
But this is a reasonable way,
where we can adapt
the BM25 retrieval model
for paradigmatical
relation mining.
In this case, we define the
document vector as containing
elements representing
normalized BM25 values.
So in this
normalization function,
we take sum over all
the words and we
normalize the weight of
each word by the sum
of the weights of all the words.
This is to again ensure all the
xi's will sum to
one in this vector.
So this would be very similar
to what we had before,
in that this vector is
actually something similar
to a word distribution,
all the xi's will sum to one.
Now, the weight of BM25 for
each word is defined here.
If you compare this with
our old definition where we just
have a normalized count
of this one, right?
So we only have this one
and the document lens or
the total counts of words in
that context to document,
and that's what we had before.
But now with the BM25
transformation,
we introduced something else.
First, of course,
this extra occurrence of
this count is just to
achieve the sub-linear
normalization.
But we also see we introduced
the parameter, k, here,
and this parameter is
generally a non-active number,
although zero is also possible.
But this controls
the upper bound,
and also controls to what extent
it simulates the
linear transformation.
So this is one parameter,
but we also see there is
another parameter here,
b, and this would be
within zero and one.
This is a parameter to
control lens normalization.
In this case,
the normalization formula has
a average document lens here.
This is computed up
by taking the average
of the lenses of all the
documents in the collection.
In this case, all the lenses of
all the context of documents
that we're considering.
So this average documents
will be a constant for
any given collection.
So it actually is only
affecting the effect
of the parameter,
b, here because
this is a constant.
But I kept it here because
it's a constant that's used
for in retrieval where it would
give us a stabilized
interpretation of parameter, b.
But for our purpose,
this will be a constant so
it would only be affecting
the lens normalization
together with parameter, b.
Now, with this definition then,
we have a new way to define
our document of vectors,
and we can compute
the vector d2 in the same way.
The difference is that
the high-frequency terms will now
have a somewhat lower weights.
This would help us control
the inference of
these high-frequency terms.
Now, the idea can be added
here in the scoring function.
That means we'll
introduce a weight
for matching each term.
So you may recall
this sum indicates
all the possible words
that can be
overlap between the two contexts.
The x_i and the y_i
are probabilities
of picking the word
from both contexts.
Therefore, it
indicates how likely
we'll see a match on this word.
Now, IDF would give us
the importance of
matching this word.
A common word will be worth
less than a rare word.
So we emphasize more on
matching rare words now.
So with this modification,
then the new function will
likely address
those two problems.
Now, interestingly
we can also use
this approach to discover
syntagmatic relations.
In general, when we re-brand
a context with a term vector,
we would likely see
some terms have high weights
and other terms have low weights.
Depending on how we assign
weights to these terms,
we might be able to
use these weights to
discover the words that
are strongly associated with
the candidate word
in the context.
So let's take a look at
the term vector in
more detail here.
We have each x_i
defined as the normalized
weight of BM25.
Now, this weight alone only
reflects how frequent the word
occurs in the context.
But we can't just say
any frequent term in
the context that would
be correlated with
the candidate word because
many common words like 'the' will
occur frequently in
all the context.
But if we apply IDF
weighting as you see here,
we can then re-weight
these terms based on IDF.
That means the words that are
common like 'the'
will get penalized.
So now the highest
weighted terms will not be
those common terms because
they have lower IDFs.
Instead, those terms would
be the terms that are
frequent in the context,
but not frequent
in the collection.
So those are clearly the words
that tend to occur in
the context of the candidate
word, for example, cat.
So for this reason,
the highly weighted terms in
this idea of weighted vector
can also be assumed to
be candidates for
syntagmatic relations.
Now, of course, this is
only a by-product of
our approach for discovering
paradigmatic relations.
In the next lecture, we're
going to talk more about
how to discover
syntagmatic relations.
But it clearly shows the relation
between discovering
the two relations.
Indeed they can be discovered in
a joint manner by leveraging
such associations.
So to summarize,
the main idea for discovering
paradigmatic relations is to
collect the context of
a candidate word to
form a pseudo document.
This is typically represented
as a bag of words.
Then compute the similarity of
the corresponding
context documents
of two candidate words.
Then we can take
the highly similar word pairs,
and treat them as having
paradigmatic relations.
These are the words that
share similar contexts.
There are many different ways to
implement this general idea.
We just talked about
some of the approaches.
More specifically, we
talked about using
text retrieval models to help us
design effective
similarity function to
compute the
paradigmatic relations.
More specifically, we have used
the BM25 and IDF weighting
to discover
paradigmatic relation.
These approaches also represent
the state of the art in
text retrieval techniques.
Finally, syntagmatic relations
can also be discovered
as a by-product when we discover
paradigmatic relations.